Guide to the Theater programs from East Germany, 1951-1973
Department of Special Collections
Theater programs from East Germany,
1951-1973
M0644
2 linear ft. (186 items)
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Collection of theater programs from the former GDR. Includes important performances of the time, including plays of classical repertoire (Schiller, Goethe, Lessing, Goldoni) as well as modern (Brecht, Gorki, Bredel). Each program includes the cast, extensive descriptions, and quotations from the classics of Marxist ideology intended to educate the spectator.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1992.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Collection of theater programs from the former GDR. Includes important performances of the time, including plays of classical repertoire (Schiller, Goethe, Lessing, Goldoni) as well as modern (Brecht, Gorki, Bredel). Each program includes the cast, extensive descriptions, and quotations from the classics of Marxist ideology intended to educate the spectator.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Berliner Ensemble (Berlin); Deutsches Nationaltheater (Weimar); Deutsches Theater (Berlin); Maxim Gorki Theater (Berlin); Metropol (Berlin); Theater am Schiffbauerdamm (Berlin); Theater der Freundschaft (Berlin); Volksbèuhne (Berlin, Germany); Volksbuhne (Rostock); Philosophy, Marxist.; Theater--East Germany.
Collection Contents
- Deutsches Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, Authors A-F, 1952-1964, 6 programs (Box 1, Folder 1)
  The Büchner program includes a play by Carl Orff. The program Julius Fucik, play by Jurij Burjakovski, contains a lot of information about Fucik
  Besson, Benno. Director.; Aristophanes. Der Frieden.; Beaumarchais, Pierre Augustin Caron de, 1732-1799. Der tolle Tag, oder Wenn Figaro Hochzeit macht.; Friedrich, Götz. Director.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Intendant.; Burjakovski, Jurij. Julius Fucik.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Director.; Bernhardy, Werner. Ein Polterabend.; Bois, Curt. Director.; Bill-Belozerkowski, Vladimir, 1885-1970. Storm.; Büchner, Georg, 1813-1837. Woyzeck.; Orff, Carl. Astutuli.
- Deutsches Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, Authors G, 1951-1971, 9 programs (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832. Egmont.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Intendant.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Director.; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832. Faust I.; Dresen, Adolf. Director.; Heinz, Wolfgang. Director.; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832. Iphigenie auf Tauris.; Gogol, Nikolai, 1809-1852. Tagebuch eines Wahnsinnigen.; Gorky, Maksim, 1868-1936. Jegor Bulytschov und die Anderen.; Jungbauer, Hans. Director.; Gorky, Maksim, 1868-1936. Die Kleinbürger.; Paryla, Karl. Director.; Gorky, Maksim, 1868-1936. Ssomow und Andere.
- Deutsches Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, Authors H-I, 1952-1972, 10 programs (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Hauptmann, GerhardJohann Robert, 1862-1946. Vor Sonnenuntergang.; Heinz, Wolfgang. Director.; Hacks, Peter, 1928. Adam und Eva.; Hacks, Peter, 1928. Amphitryon.; Solto, Friedo. Director.; Hacks, Peter, 1928. Columbus oder Eröffnung des indischen Zeitalt; Kahler, Ernst. Director.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Intendant.; Hacks, Peter, 1928. Die Schlacht bei Lobositz.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Director.; Hauser, Harald, 1912. Prozess Wedding.; Hikmet, Nazim, 1902-1963. Ein komischer Mensch.; Trösch, Robert. Director.; Isaev, Konstantin. Vas vyoyvaet tainyr.; Galich, Alexander. Vas vyoyvaet teinyr.; Ibsen, Henrik, 1828-1906. Nora oder ein Puppenheim.; Hanau, John. Director.; Hikmet, Nazim, 1902-1963. Legende von der Liebe.; Gliese, Rochus. Director.
- Deutsches Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, Authors K, 1951-1974, 8 programs (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Kana, Vasek. Brigade Karhan.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Intendant.; Kant, Hermann. Die Aula.; Birnbaum, Uta. Director.; Heinz, Wolfgang. Intendant.; Kirsch, Sarah. Die Pantherfrau.; Kornejtschuk, Aleksandr. Der Chirurg.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Director.; Kroetz, Franz Xaver. Oberösterreich.; Stillmark, Alexander. Director.; Kron, Aleksandr, 1909. Das tote Tal.; Grosse, Herwart. Director.
- Deutsches Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, Authors L-R,1951-1968, 11 programs (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Lessing, Gotthold Ephraim,d1729-1781. Minna von Barnhelm.; Jungbauer, Hans. Director.; Lessing, Gotthold Ephraim,d1729-1781. Nathan der Weise.; Holtz, Jürgen. Director.; Heinz, Wolfgang. Intendant.; Lorca, Frederico Garcia. Bernarda Albas Haus.; Maltz, Albert, 1908-. Hotelboy Ed Martin.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Intendant.; Menzel, Gerhard W, 1922-. Marek im Westen.; Dissel, Werner. Director.; Moliere, Jean-Baptiste Poquelin, 1622-1673. Malade imaginaire.; O'Casey, Sean, 1880-1964. The Shadow of a Gunman.; Wessely, Rudolf. Director.; Moliere, Jean-Baptiste Poquelin, 1622-1673. Der Tartuff.; Besson, Benno. Director.; Heinz, Wolfgang. Intendant.; Ostrovskii, Aleksandr Nicolaeviki, 1823-1886. Tolles Geld.; Wendel, Fritz. Director.; Remarque, Erich Maria, 1898-1970. Die letzte Station.; Stöhr, Emil. Director.; Rosov, Viktor, 1913-. Unterwegs.
- Deutsches Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, Authors Salomon-Shakespeare, 1951-1968, 9 programs (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Salomon, Horst. Ein Lorbass.; Heinz, Wolfgang. Intendant.; Besson, Benno. Director.; Schiller, Friedrich, 1759-1835. Don Carlos.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Director.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Intendant.; Schiller, Friedrich, 1759-1835. Kabale und Liebe.; Scholochow, Michael. Neuland unterm Pflug.; Shvarts, Evgenii, 1896-1958. Der Drache.; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616. Hamlet.; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616. King Lear.; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616. Othello.; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616. As You Like It.
- Deutsches Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, Authors Shaw-Suassuna,1951-1974, 8 programs (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Shaw, George Bernard, 1856-1950. Androcles and the Lion.; Shaw, George Bernard, 1856-1950. Candida.; Shaw, George Bernard, 1856-1950. Frau Warrens Gewerbe.; Shaw, George Bernard, 1856-1950. Heartbreak House.; Shaw, George Bernard, 1856-1950. Der Mann des Schicksals.; Shaw, George Bernard, 1856-1950. Blanco Posnets Erweckung.; Shaw, George Bernard, 1856-1950. Pygmalion.; Silva, Francisco Ribeiro da, 1810-1876. Chap-en-de-Sebo.; Suassuna, Ariano. Auto da compadecida.; Kipphardt, Heinar. Director.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Intendant.; Heinz, Wolfgang. Director.; Paryla, Karl. Director.; Solter, Friedo. Director.; Noelte, Rudolf. Director.
- Deutsches Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, Authors T-Z,1951-1965, 9 programs (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Tarn, Adam. Ein ungewöhnlicher Fall.; Tolstoy, Leo Nicolaevich Graf, 1828-1910. Voskresenie.; Vega, Lope de, 1562-1635. Das Dorf Fuente Ovejuna.; Vailland, Roger. Colonel Foster ist schuldig.; Zapolska, Gabriela. Die Moral der Frau Dulski.; Grosse, Herwart. Director.; Langhoff, Wolfgang. Intendant.; Paryla, Karl. Director.; Heinz, Wolfgang. Director.; Wessely, Rudolf. Director.; Schönemann, Horst. Director.; Literatur im Widerstand 1933-1945.
- Berliner Ensemble (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1957-1971, 9 programs. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Baierl, Helmut. Johanna von Döbeln.; Becher, Johannes. Winterschlacht.; Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-. Der aufhaltsame Aufstieg des Arturo Ui.; Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-. Die Dreigroschenoper.; Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-. Die Gewehre der Frau Carrar.; Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-. Der gute Mensch von Sezuan.; Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-. Der kaukasische Kreidekreis.; Brecht, Bertolt. Director.; Wekwerth, Manfred. Director.; Besson, Benno. Director.
- Berliner Ensemble (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1951-1959, 6 programs (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-. Das Leben des Galilei.; Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-. Die Mutter.; Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-. Mutter Courage und ihre Kinder.; Bertolt Brecht.; Büchner, Georg. Woyzeck.; Brecht, Bertolt. Director.; Nitzschke, Helmut. Director.
- Berliner Ensemble (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1964-1972., 11 programs. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Farquhar, George, 1678-1707. The Recruiting Officer.; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832. Urfaust.; Moliere, Jean-Baptiste Poquelin, 1622-1673. Don Juan.; Ostrowski, Aleksanr Nikolajewitsch, 1823-1886. Die Ziehtochter oder Wohltaten tun weh.; Pogodin, Nicolai Fiodorowitch. Das Glockenspiel des Kreml.; Seghers, Anna, 1900-. Der Prozess der Jeanne d'Arc zu Rouen 1431.; Shakespeare, Willaim, 1564-1616. Die Tragödie des Coriolan.; Strittmatter, Erwin. Katzengraben.; Vishnevsky, Vsevolod. Optimistische Tragödie.; Besson, Benno. Director.; Monk, Egon. Director.; Hurwicz, Angelika. Director.; Busch, Ernst. Director.; Wekwerth, Manfred. Director.; Tenschert, Joachim. Director.; Brecht, Bertolt. Director.; Tragelehn, B.K. Director.
- Volksbühne (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1954-1974, 11 programs. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Calderon, Pedro de la Barca Barreda Gonzales, 1600-1681. Der Richter von Zalamea.; Diderot, Denis, 1713-1784. Rameaus Neffe.; Goldoni, Carlo, 1707-1793. Der Diener zeier Herren.; Hacks, Peter. Margarete in Aix.; Ibsen, Henrik, 1828-1906. Die Wildente.; Kohout, Pavel, 1928-. Taxova laska.; Majakovsky, Vladimir, 1893-1930. Das Schwitzbad.; Mesterhazy, Lajos. Menschen von Budapest.; Orkeny, Istvan. Katzenspiel.; Ostrovsky. Wald.; Hellberg, Martin. Director.; Tausig, Otto. Director.; Besson, Benno. Director.; Holan, Karl. Intendant.; Wisten, Fritz. Director.; Karge, Manfred. Director.; Langhoff, Matthias. Director.
- Volksbühne (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1954-1972, 7 programs. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Sartre, Jean Paul. Nekrassow.; Schiller, Friedrich, 1759-1835. Die Räuber.; Schiller, Friedrich, 1759-1835. Wilhelm Tell.; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616. Othello.; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616. A Midsummer Night's Dream.; Shaw, George Bernard, 1856-1950. Caesar and Cleopatra.; Langhoff, Mattias. Director.; Wisten, Fritz. Director.; Karge, Manfred. Director.; Tausig, Otto. Director.; Bennewitz, Fritz. Director.; Gaillard, Ottofritz. Director.
- Volksbühne (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1955-1972, 7 items: 4 programs, 1 season catalogue and 2 posters. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Weiss, Peter. Die Verfolgung und Ermordung Jean Paul Marats dargestellt durch die Schauspielgruppe des Hospizes zu Charenton unter Anleitung des Herrn de Sade.; Winterlich, Gerhard. Horizonte.; Wischnewski, Wsewolod. Die erste Reiterarmee.; Zinner, Hedda. Was wäre, wenn?.; Langhoff, Mattias. Director.; Karge, Manfred. Director.; Besson, Benno. Director.; Holan, Karl. Intendant.; Jung-Alsen, Kurt. Director.; Bornemann, Fritz. Director.; Tausing, Otto. Director.; Wisten, Fritz. Intendant.
- Maxim Gorki Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1953-1957, 6 programs (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Aristorphanes. Lysistrata.; Blach, Erich. Sturmflut.; Caragiale, Ion Luca, 1852-1912. O scriseare pierduta.; Gorky, Maksim, 1868-1936. Barbaren.; Gorky, Maksim, 1868-1936. Dotigajew und Andere.; Gorky, Maksim, 1868-1936. Feinde.; Littlewood, Joan. Director.; Wolfram, Gerhard. Director.; Bortfeldt, Hans-Robert. Director.; Vallentin, Maxim. Intendant.; Vallentin, Maxim. Director.; Mäde, Hans-Dieter. Director.; Hetterle, Albert. Director.
- Maxim Gorki Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1952-1962, 5 programs (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Hauptmann, Gerhard, 1862-1946. Der Biberpelz.; Hay, Julius, 1900-. Energie.; Lavrenev, Boris, 1891-1959. Za Tex, kio buope.; Mesterhazy, Lajos. Das elfte Gebot.; Popov, Ivanovich Vasilevich, 1885-1961.; Schulz-Wittan, Werner. Director.; Lang, Otto. Director.; Vallentin, Maxim. Intendant.; Schöbel, Helfried. Director.
- Maxim Gorki Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1952-1969, 5 programs (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616. The Comedy of Errors.; Shatrov, Michael. Bolsheviki.; Stehlik, Miroslav. Der Weg ins Leben.; Wolf, Friedrich August, 1888-1953. Das Schiff auf der Donau.; Vallentin, Maxim. Intendant.; Bortfeldt, Hans-Robert. Director.; Schulz-Wittan, Werner. Director.; Vallentin, Maxim. Director.; Bornemann, Fritz. Director.
- Theater am Schiffbauerdamm (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1951-1954, 7 programs. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Gogol, Nikolai Vasilevich, 1809-1852. Die Heirat.; Goldoni, Carlo, 1707-1793. Der Brauthandel.; Gorky, Maksim, 1868-1936. Die Feinde.; Karras, Peter, 1920-. Menschen unserer Strasse.; Molina, Tirso de, 1571-1648. Marta la Piadosa.; Tank, Herb. Tanker Nebraska.; Zinner, Hedda. Der Teufelskreis.; Wisten, Fritz. Director.; Kutschera, Franz. Director.; Jung-Alsen, Kurt. Director.; Herrmann, Gottfried. Director.
- Friedrichstadtpalast Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1958, 1 program. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Feier zu Ehren von Paul Robeson.
- Komödie Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1958, 1 program. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Magnier, Claude. Monsier Masure.; Wölfer, Hans. Director.
- Metropol Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1953, 3 programs (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Wangenheim, Gustav von. An beiden Ufern der Spree.; Hermecke, Hermann. Doktor Eisenblatt.; Offenbach, Jacques, 1819-1880. Die Banditen.; Pitra, Hans. Intendant.
- Schauspielschule (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1952, 1 program (Box 3, Folder 8)
  Kavertin, Veniamin, 1902-. Zwei Kapitäne.; Gööck, Dieter. Director.
- Schiller-Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1951-1952, 2 programs (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Sartre, Jean Paul, 1905-. Le diable et le bon dieu.; Camus, Albert, 1913-1960. L'Etat de Siege.; Barlog, Boleslav. Intendant.
- Schlosspark-Theater (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1951-1952, 2 programs (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Anouilh, Jean, 1910-. Colombe.; Becher, Ulrich. Samba.; Käutner, Helmuth. Director.
- Theater am Kurfürstendamm (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1951-1952, 1 program (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Hauptmann, Gerhart, 1862-1946. Herbert Engelmann.; Kurth, Otto. Director.
- Theater der Freundschaft (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1958-1959, 3 programs. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Schiller, Johann Christoph Friedrich, 1759-1805. Kabale und Liebe.; Michalkov, Sergei. Das rote Halstuch.; Küchenmeister, Wera. Damals 18/19.; Küchenmeister, Claus. Damals 18/19.; Bellag, Lothar. Director.; Rodenberg, Hans. Intendant.; Menzel, Siegfried. Director.; Rodenberg, Hans. Director.
- Berliner Festtage (Berlin, Germany) Programs, 1958, 1 program (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Music, film, cabaret, ballet, and theater performances for the November, 1958 10. Jahrestage des Demokratischen Berlin.
- Tribüne 10 (Berlin, Germany). Programs, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  1 pamphlet on types of theater performances.
- Landestheater Altenburg (Altenburg, Germany). Programs, 1950 - 1951, 2 programs (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Reutter, Hermann. Kirmes von Delft.; Orff, Carl. Die Kluge.; Turgenev, Ivan Sergeevich, 1818-1883. Mesiats v derevne.; Jung-Alsen, Kurt. Intendant.; Jung-Alsen, Kurt. Director.
- Cottbus Stadttheater (Cottbus, Germany). Programs, 1951-1953, 2 programs (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Pagnol, Marcel, 1895-1974. Das grosse ABC.; Gericke, Konrad. Intendant.; Rabe, Kurt. Director.
- Landestheater Dessau (Dessau, Germany). Programs, 1952, 1 program (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Kubsch, Hermann Werner. Die ersten Schritte.; Kubsch, Hermann Werner. Director.
- Staatstheater Dresden (Dresden, Germany). Programs, 1952, 1 program (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Special week on Classical heritage.
  Woche des Klassischen Erbes.; Schiller, Friedrich, 1759-1835. Wilhelm Tell.; Weber, Carl Maria von, 1786-1826. Der Freischütz.; Lessing, Gotthold Ephraim, 1729-1781. Emilia Galotti.; Lessing, Gotthold Ephraim, 1729-1781. Minna von Barnhelm.; Hauptmann, Gerhart, 1862-1946. Die Weber.; Lortzing, Albert, 1801-1851. Der Wildschütz.; Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832. Iphigenie auf Tauris.; Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus. Cosi fan Tutte.
- Kleist-Theater (Frankfurt a.O., Germany). Programs,1963-1964, 1 program. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Olmo, Lauro. La Camisa.; Rüdiger, Carl. Director.
- Laienspielstudio (Leipzig, Germany) Programs, 1958, 1 program. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Baierl, Helmut Johannes. Die Feststellung, ein Lehrstück.
- Leipziger Stadttheater (Leipzig, Germany). Programs, 1952-1960, 3 programs. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Becher, Johannes Robert, 1891-1958. Winterschlacht.; Gorky, Maksim, 1868-1936. Die Letzten.; Rolland, Romain, 1866-1944. Robespierre.; Burghardt, Max. Director.; Jopp, Arthur. Director.; Burghardt, Max. Intendant.; Ruede, Fritz, Director.; Curth, Johannes. Director.
- Hans-Otto-Theater (Potsdam, Germany). Programs, 1953-1954, 1 program. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Goldoni, Carlo, 1707-1793. Das Kaffeehaus.; Weintrad, Ilse. Director.
- Volkstheater Rostock (Rostock, Germany). Programs, 1952-1974, 5 programs (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Goodrich, Frances. The Diary of Anne Frank.; Moliere, Jean-Baptiste Poquelin, 1621-1673. Don Juan.; Streubel, Manfred. Ratcliff rechnet ab.; Vellejo, Antonio Buero. El sueno de la razon.; Weiss, Peter. Hölderlin.; Richter, Alexander. Director.; Allmeroth, Heinrich. Intendant.; Perten, Hans Anselm. Director.
- Salzland-Theater (Stassfurt, Germany). Programs, 1954, 1 program (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Waterstradt, Berta. Ehesache Lorenz.; Merten, Rolf. Director.
- Theater der Werftstadt (Stralsund, Germany) Programs, 1958-1959, 1 program. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Rosov, Viktor Sergeevich. Vpaiskakh radati.; Hermann, Hugo. Director.
- Deutsches Nationaltheater (Weimar, Germany). Programs, 1955-1970, 2 programs (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-1956. Die Gewehre der Frau Carrar.; Schiller, Friedrich, 1759-1835. Wallenstein.; Lang, Otto. Intendant.; Kayser, Karl. Director.